<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Conservation on Fernando Alonso Campos</title>
    <link>/tags/conservation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Conservation on Fernando Alonso Campos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Fernando Campos</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 22:33:41 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/conservation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Population dynamics</title>
      <link>/project/population-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2019 22:33:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/population-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>I am interested in how primate populations change over time as their habitats and climates change. We have carried out repeated large-scale censuses of primates in the ACG to monitor changes in the capuchin and howler monkey populations over time. This work spans several decades (starting with early census work in 1983), and is in collaboration with Linda Fedigan, Kathy Jack, Jeremy Hogan, and others.
Hogan et. al (In Press) Am J Primatol.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservation Priorities</title>
      <link>/project/conservation-priorities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2008 22:46:31 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/conservation-priorities/</guid>
      <description>Distribution and abundance of the Ecuadorian capuchin The Ecuadorian capuchin (Cebus albifrons aequatorialis) is a critically endangered primate found only in the fragmented forests of western Ecuador and northern Peru, which are among the most imperiled ecosystems on earth. Together with Katharine Jack of Tulane University, I carried out surveys across western Ecuador for C. a. aequatorialis. We have described several new presence localities as well as habitat preferences for this rare and poorly-studied primate.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>