<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Campos Lab @ UTSA</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Campos Lab @ UTSA</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu6c58ab13c7e55bee62cd05fd713a71a0_1309_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Campos Lab @ UTSA</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Long-term Animal Research Seminar Series</title>
      <link>/talk/long-term-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Jun 2020 12:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/long-term-research/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Comparing Proportional and Ordinal Dominance Ranks Reveals Multiple Competitive Landscapes in an Animal Society</title>
      <link>/publication/levy-comparing-proportional-ordinal-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/levy-comparing-proportional-ordinal-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Aging</title>
      <link>/project/aging/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 22:55:21 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/aging/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Foraging and nutritional ecology</title>
      <link>/project/foraging-nutritional-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Apr 2020 22:38:46 -0500</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/foraging-nutritional-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;A major area of uncertainty regarding how primates will respond to climate change involves their interactions with plant foods. Interaction dynamics between primates and plant food species are important because phenological shifts and loss of critical mutualisms involving plant foods as a result of climate change could lead to nutritional mismatches that compromise primates’ abilities to satisfy their dietary requirements. Many primates play key roles in their ecological communities through seed dispersal, folivory, and pollination. Therefore improvements in our understanding of primate–plant interaction dynamics under climate change can contribute to far-reaching conservation efforts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together with collaborators 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amandamelin.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amanda Melin&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://urskalbitzer.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Urs Kalbitzer&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Jeremy_Hogan&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Jeremy Hogan&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Nigel_Parr2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nigel Parr&lt;/a&gt;, and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mackenziebergstrom.wordpress.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Mackenzie Bergstrom&lt;/a&gt;, I have been working to understand the spatiotemporal distribution of primate food nutrients in the Área de Conservación Guanacaste (ACG), Costa Rica.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://camposfa.github.io/pace-fruit-biomass.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;algorithms for estimating fruit biomass&lt;/a&gt;, which draw on multiple botanical and behavioral data sets, are a cornerstone of recent ecological research on the ACG&amp;rsquo;s capuchin population.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/bergstromnoninvasiveestimationcosts-2020/&#34;&gt;Bergstrom et al. (2020). &lt;em&gt;Horm Behav&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Differential Impact of Severe Drought on Infant Mortality in Two Sympatric Neotropical Primates</title>
      <link>/publication/camposdifferentialimpactsevere-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/camposdifferentialimpactsevere-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non-Invasive Estimation of the Costs of Feeding Competition in a Neotropical Primate</title>
      <link>/publication/bergstromnoninvasiveestimationcosts-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/bergstromnoninvasiveestimationcosts-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Costs of Competition: High Social Status Males Experience Accelerated Epigenetic Aging in Wild Baboons</title>
      <link>/publication/andersoncostscompetitionhigh-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/andersoncostscompetitionhigh-2020/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Group versus Population Level Demographics: An Analysis of Comparability Using Long Term Data on Wild White-faced Capuchin Monkeys (Cebus capucinus imitator)</title>
      <link>/publication/hogangrouppopulationlevel-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/hogangrouppopulationlevel-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Population Dynamics</title>
      <link>/project/population-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jun 2019 22:33:41 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/population-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;dynamics-of-primate-populations-in-the-acg&#34;&gt;Dynamics of Primate Populations in the ACG&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am interested in how primate populations change over time as their habitats and climates change. We have carried out repeated large-scale censuses of primates in the ACG to monitor changes in the capuchin and howler monkey populations over time. This work spans several decades (starting with early census work in 1983), and is in collaboration with Linda Fedigan, Kathy Jack, Jeremy Hogan, and others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/hogangrouppopulationlevel-2019/&#34;&gt;Hogan et. al (2019) &lt;em&gt;Am J Primatol&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/camposclimateoscillationsconservation-2015/&#34;&gt;Campos et. al (2015) &lt;em&gt;Biol Conserv&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seasonality of the Gut Microbiota of Free-Ranging White-Faced Capuchins in a Tropical Dry Forest</title>
      <link>/publication/orkinseasonalitygutmicrobiota-2019/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/orkinseasonalitygutmicrobiota-2019/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add your privacy policy here and set &lt;code&gt;draft: false&lt;/code&gt; to publish it. Otherwise, delete this file if you don&amp;rsquo;t need it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terms</title>
      <link>/terms/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>/terms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Add your terms here and set &lt;code&gt;draft: false&lt;/code&gt; to publish it. Otherwise, delete this file if you don&amp;rsquo;t need it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Synthesis of Long-Term Environmental Change in Santa Rosa, Costa Rica</title>
      <link>/publication/campos-synthesis-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/campos-synthesis-2018/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate variability and vital rates</title>
      <link>/project/climate-variability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 22:33:41 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/climate-variability/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;There is a growing need to understand how threatened species are affected by climate variability and climate change. This knowledge can uncover the limits of resiliency to climatic fluctuations and set the stage for informed conservation efforts. My colleagues and I have published important findings about how demography in natural primate populations varies in response to climate variability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first project with the 
&lt;a href=&#34;/project/plhd/&#34;&gt;PLHD working group&lt;/a&gt; examined the effects of temperature, rainfall, and large-scale climate oscillations on vital rates, including annual birth rates and survival rates. We found strong climate signals in the birth rates of three species. These results inform our understanding of ways in which climate change could affect the future fates of wild primates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/camposdoesclimatevariability-2017/&#34;&gt;Campos et. al (2017) &lt;em&gt;Glob Change Biol&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am especially interested in how animal populations are affected by cyclical, large-scale weather patterns, like the El Niño Southern Oscillation (ENSO), that can bring rare but recurrent severe drought. Using three decades of census, life-history, and climate data from the Santa Rosa capuchins, I uncovered evidence of population demographic responses to climate in the form of lagged declines in female fertility rates following rainfall deficits associated with ENSO. This finding has important conservation implications because ENSO cycles are predicted to increase in frequency and severity during the next century.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/camposclimateoscillationsconservation-2015/&#34;&gt;Campos et. al (2015) &lt;em&gt;Biol Conserv&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primate Life History Database</title>
      <link>/project/plhd/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 22:33:41 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/plhd/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h4 id=&#34;background-on-the-working-group&#34;&gt;Background on the Working Group&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://plhdb.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Primate Life History Database&lt;/a&gt; is a unique compilation of full life-course information from seven wild populations that have been studied for at least 30 years. The database contains standardized records for thousands of individual primates that have been followed from birth to death. These primate populations are some of the best-studied wild primates on earth. Formed over the course of several meetings from 2005 to 2007, the original core members of the PLHD include co-organizers Susan Alberts and Karen Strier, along with Jeanne Altmann, Diane Brockman, Anne Bronikowski, Marina Cords, Linda Fedigan, Bill Morris, Anne Pusey, Tara Stoinski. Following Diane&amp;rsquo;s retirement, Rich Lawler joined the working group in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/cards/plhd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;PLHD Working Group&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My involvement with the PLHD working group began in 2015, when I was brought in to investigate the question of how &amp;ldquo;vital rates&amp;rdquo;—that is, birth rates and death rates—are affected by climate variability. This culminated in our 2017 paper:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/camposdoesclimatevariability-2017/&#34;&gt;Campos et al. (2017) &lt;em&gt;Global Change Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a post-doc in Susan Alberts&amp;rsquo; lab at Duke, I continued to work on several unresolved questions about life history evolution using this exceptionally valuable resource.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Early Life Adversity</title>
      <link>/project/early-life-adversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 22:32:38 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/early-life-adversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adversity during early life can reach far into the future to exert profound effects on health and well-being during adulthood.
Striking parallels exist between early-life effects in humans and in natural animal populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The leading conceptual models for early-life effects propose different evolutionary explanations for these phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developmental constraints models&lt;/strong&gt; propose that harsh early-life conditions lead to developmental tradeoffs that prioritize immediate survival at the cost of reduced health, reproduction, and/or survival later in life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predictive adaptive response (PAR) models&lt;/strong&gt; posit that early-life conditions provide cues for predicting future conditions, leading to adaptive responses during development that maximize evolutionary fitness under predicted conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are several important gaps in our understanding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;, which of these frameworks best explains the emergence of early-life effects in nonhuman primates?
&lt;strong&gt;Second&lt;/strong&gt;, to what extent are such effects embedded in our evolutionary history?
&lt;strong&gt;Third&lt;/strong&gt;, what are the optimal approaches to mitigating disparities in health and well-being that result from exposure early-life adversity in humans?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motivated by these questions, I am leveraging a 
&lt;a href=&#34;/project/plhd/&#34;&gt;database of life history data&lt;/a&gt; on seven natural primate populations to shed light on the mechanisms that underlie the far-reaching effects of early-life adversity and to test the universality of these effects among close relatives of humans.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Environmental Stressors</title>
      <link>/project/environmental-stressors/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2017 21:10:49 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/environmental-stressors/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;drought-and-primate-infant-mortality&#34;&gt;Drought and primate infant mortality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Extreme climate events can have important consequences for the dynamics of natural populations, and severe droughts are predicted to become more common and intense due to climate change. We analysed infant mortality in relation to drought and fruit abundance using long-term data. During severe drought, we see high capuchin infant mortality, and spider monkeys stop reproducing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/camposdifferentialimpactsevere-2020/&#34;&gt;Campos et al. (2020) &lt;em&gt;Roy Soc Open Sci&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;climate-seasonality&#34;&gt;Climate Seasonality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate seasonality poses unique challenges to long-lived organisms in tropical dry forests: they must tolerate both long dry periods and long wet periods, and they must cope with the variable timing of transitions between wet and dry seasons. My colleagues and I have published studies that document how these challenges are met in a population of arboreal monkeys. These studies provided new insights into the strategies and behavioral tactics used by organisms to contend with periodic biophysical adversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seasonality in the tropical dry forests of Costa Rica is exceptionally strong. Although the region receives about 1,700 mm of rain each year, the rainfall is almost entirely confined to a 5-6 month wet season with moderate temperatures and lush vegetation. By contrast, the dry season—with its high temperatures and extreme scarcity of surface water—can be a difficult time for the primates. To conserve water, most trees in the forest lose their leaves, exposing the monkeys to intense solar radiation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/plots/seasonality-map.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;seasonality&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I review these climatic processes in a book chapter: 
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/campos-synthesis-2018/&#34;&gt;Campos (2018) &lt;em&gt;Primate Life Histories, Sex Roles, and Adaptability - Essays in Honour of Linda M. Fedigan.&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;behavioral-thermoregulation&#34;&gt;Behavioral Thermoregulation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My Master&amp;rsquo;s research examined the behavioral strategies that the capuchins use to cope with this extreme seasonality. I found that they reduce activity during the hottest hours of the day, and they concentrate their movements around the few remaining sources of surface water. They also extend their tongues in hot dry conditions, presumably to cool themselves via evaporation of saliva from the tongue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/camposbehavioraladaptationsheat-2009/&#34;&gt;Campos and Fedigan (2009) &lt;em&gt;Am J Phys Anth&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;seasonal-changes-in-the-gut-microbiome&#34;&gt;Seasonal Changes in the Gut Microbiome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My collaborators 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://josephorkin.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Joseph Orkin&lt;/a&gt; and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amandamelin.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Amanda Melin&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Calgary are directing a study, on which I am collaborating, that aims to understand temporal variation in the composition of the capuchin gut microbiome, and how these changes are related to resource availability and rainfall patterns. New completed work in this area is currently in review.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/orkinseasonalitygutmicrobiota-2019/&#34;&gt;Orkin et al. (2018) &lt;em&gt;The ISME J&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Howler Monkey Foraging Ecology Suggests Convergent Evolution of Routine Trichromacy as an Adaptation for Folivory</title>
      <link>/publication/melinhowlermonkeyforaging-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/melinhowlermonkeyforaging-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Female Sociality and Sexual Conflict Shape Offspring Survival in a Neotropical Primate</title>
      <link>/publication/kalbitzerfemalesocialitysexual-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/kalbitzerfemalesocialitysexual-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Does Climate Variability Influence the Demography of Wild Primates? Evidence from Long-Term Life-History Data in Seven Species</title>
      <link>/publication/camposdoesclimatevariability-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/camposdoesclimatevariability-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Habitat Restoration</title>
      <link>/publication/campos-habitat-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/campos-habitat-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inbreeding Avoidance and Female Mate Choice Shape Reproductive Skew in Capuchin Monkeys (Cebus capucinus imitator)</title>
      <link>/publication/wikberginbreedingavoidancefemale-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/wikberginbreedingavoidancefemale-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vigilance, Sentinels, and Alarms</title>
      <link>/publication/campos-vigilance-2017/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/campos-vigilance-2017/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Movement Ecology</title>
      <link>/project/movement-ecology/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Sep 2015 14:16:02 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/movement-ecology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;No wild animal roams at random over the country: each has a home region, even if it has not an actual home.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;    &amp;mdash; Ernest Thompson Seton, 1909&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;determinants-of-home-range-behavior-in-capuchins&#34;&gt;Determinants of home range behavior in capuchins&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What factors determine how and where animals use space? What determines the size and shape of their &amp;ldquo;home range?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Motivated by these question, I compiled a large eight-year data set (collected by myself and by many collaborators on separate projects) representing over 20,000 contact hours on seven social groups of white-faced capuchins. The data consist of GPS tracking locations, behavioral observations, and various kinds of environmental data, including climate and habitat variables. I used a 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.plosone.org/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0014592&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;movement-based kernel method&lt;/a&gt; to calculate home ranges at four nested temporal scales and three nested spatial scales, and I examined the social and environmental factors that drive home range dynamics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our work examined how variation in climate, food abundance, and group size affects the area of the home range, and the types of habitats contained within the home range.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/camposdrivershomerange-2014-a/&#34;&gt;Campos et al. (2014) &lt;em&gt;Anim Behav&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/cards/home-range.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Link to paper&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Social Bonds</title>
      <link>/project/social-bonds/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2015 22:33:58 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/social-bonds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In group-living animals, an individual’s social environment (e.g., the number and quality of social bonds) can have profound and far-reaching fitness consequences. For example, in many social mammals, females with higher quality or quantity of social bonds experience longer life expectancies, greater infant survival rates, and higher reproductive success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My recent interest in social connectedness grew out of work directed by my collaborator 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://urskalbitzer.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Urs Kalbitzer&lt;/a&gt; that uncovered startling evidence that female sociality in white-faced capuchins can have &lt;em&gt;negative&lt;/em&gt; fitness consequences that arise from male behavior. Specifically, highly social female capuchins are more frequently targeted in infanticidal attacks by immigrant males following a group takeover: 
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/kalbitzerfemalesocialitysexual-2017/&#34;&gt;Kalbitzer et al. (2017) &lt;em&gt;PNAS&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My postdoctoral work at Duke, pursued with Prof. 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.duke.edu/albertslab/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Susan Alberts&lt;/a&gt; and funded by 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://projectreporter.nih.gov/project_info_description.cfm?aid=9073768&amp;amp;icde=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;NIH grant 2P01AG031719-06A1&lt;/a&gt; (to 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://user.demogr.mpg.de/jwv/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;James Vaupel&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://findresearcher.sdu.dk/portal/en/persons/kaare-christensen%2835c0eca6-0f49-465b-9bbd-ce71bcf2c4ac%29.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Kaare Christensen&lt;/a&gt;, and 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.duke.edu/albertslab/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Susan Alberts&lt;/a&gt;), further explored the importance of social bonds in baboons. One of the project&amp;rsquo;s main goals was to examine the role of social integration in mediating male-female differences in health and survival during aging.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate Oscillations and Conservation Measures Regulate White-Faced Capuchin Population Growth and Demography in a Regenerating Tropical Dry Forest in Costa Rica</title>
      <link>/publication/camposclimateoscillationsconservation-2015/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/camposclimateoscillationsconservation-2015/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Effect of Male Parallel Dispersal on the Kin Composition of Groups in White-Faced Capuchins</title>
      <link>/publication/wikbergeffectmaleparallel-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/wikbergeffectmaleparallel-2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Predation risk</title>
      <link>/project/predation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Sep 2014 21:23:03 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/predation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Many animals can accurately judge fluctuations in predation risk and make behavioral adjustments to reduce their vulnerability to predators. As part of my PhD research, I used alarm-call responses by the arboreal monkey &lt;em&gt;Cebus capucinus&lt;/em&gt; to characterize perceived predation risk for three distinct predator guilds in a heterogeneous landscape. High-risk areas comprised more mature, evergreen forest. The monkeys perceived reduced risk in the high and middle forest layers, and they loosely adjusted vigilance levels to small-scale spatial variation in perceived risk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/camposspatialecologyperceived-2014/&#34;&gt;Campos and Fedigan (2014) &lt;em&gt;Behav Ecol&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drivers of Home Range Characteristics across Spatiotemporal Scales in a Neotropical Primate, Cebus capucinus</title>
      <link>/publication/camposdrivershomerange-2014-a/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/camposdrivershomerange-2014-a/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Spatial Ecology of Perceived Predation Risk and Vigilance Behavior in White-Faced Capuchins</title>
      <link>/publication/camposspatialecologyperceived-2014/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Feb 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/camposspatialecologyperceived-2014/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Potential Distribution Model and Conservation Plan for the Critically Endangered Ecuadorian Capuchin, Cebus albifrons aequatorialis</title>
      <link>/publication/campospotentialdistributionmodel-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Oct 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/campospotentialdistributionmodel-2013/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dispersal and kinship</title>
      <link>/project/dispersal-kinship/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Sep 2013 22:33:50 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/dispersal-kinship/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This project, directed by my collaborator 
&lt;a href=&#34;https://evawikberg.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Eva Wikberg&lt;/a&gt;, aims to understand the causes and consequences of sex-biased dispersal patterns. This work has challenged prevailing models that link &amp;ldquo;species-typical&amp;rdquo; dispersal with patterns of social social bondedness. Much of this work draws on molecular genetic methods, performed in the laboratories of 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.jinrui.ib.k.u-tokyo.ac.jp/kawamura-home-E.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Shoji Kawamura&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Tokyo and 
&lt;a href=&#34;http://molecular-anthro.uoregon.edu/TingLab/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Nelson Ting&lt;/a&gt; at the University of Oregon (and formerly the University of Iowa), to infer kinship and population structure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/wikberginbreedingavoidancefemale-2017/&#34;&gt;Wikberg et al. (2017), &lt;em&gt;Mol Ecol&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/wikbergeffectmaleparallel-2014/&#34;&gt;Wikberg et al. (2014), &lt;em&gt;Anim Behav&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/wikbergbetweengroupvariationfemale-2012/&#34;&gt;Wikberg et al. (2012), &lt;em&gt;PloS One&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urine-Washing in White-Faced Capuchins: A New Look at an Old Puzzle</title>
      <link>/publication/camposurinewashingwhitefacedcapuchins-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/camposurinewashingwhitefacedcapuchins-2013/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Distribution, Abundance, and Spatial Ecology of the Critically Endangered Ecuadorian Capuchin (Cebus albifrons aequatorialis).</title>
      <link>/publication/jackdistributionabundancespatial-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Jun 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/jackdistributionabundancespatial-2012/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Between-Group Variation in Female Dispersal, Kin Composition of Groups, and Proximity Patterns in a Black-and-White Colobus Monkey (Colobus vellerosus).</title>
      <link>/publication/wikbergbetweengroupvariationfemale-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/wikbergbetweengroupvariationfemale-2012/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behavioral Adaptations to Heat Stress and Water Scarcity in White-Faced Capuchins (Cebus capucinus) in Santa Rosa National Park, Costa Rica</title>
      <link>/publication/camposbehavioraladaptationsheat-2009/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2009 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/camposbehavioraladaptationsheat-2009/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Conservation Priorities</title>
      <link>/project/conservation-priorities/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Sep 2008 22:46:31 -0400</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/conservation-priorities/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h2 id=&#34;distribution-and-abundance-of-the-ecuadorian-capuchin&#34;&gt;Distribution and abundance of the Ecuadorian capuchin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Ecuadorian capuchin (&lt;em&gt;Cebus albifrons aequatorialis&lt;/em&gt;) is a critically endangered primate found only in the fragmented forests of western Ecuador and northern Peru, which are among the most imperiled ecosystems on earth. Together with Katharine Jack of Tulane University, I carried out surveys across western Ecuador for &lt;em&gt;C. a. aequatorialis&lt;/em&gt;. We have described several new presence localities as well as habitat preferences for this rare and poorly-studied primate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/jackdistributionabundancespatial-2012/&#34;&gt;Jack and Campos (2012) &lt;em&gt;Trop Conserv Sci&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;potential-distribution-and-conservation-of-the-ecuadorian-capuchin&#34;&gt;Potential distribution and conservation of the Ecuadorian capuchin&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have also modeled the potential distribution and environmental associations of &lt;em&gt;C. a. aequatorialis&lt;/em&gt;, using all known presence localities recorded within the last two decades as well as a variety of climate, topography, vegetation, and land-use GIS data sets covering the entire geographic range of the subspecies. We use this model to estimate the total carrying capacity and remaining population size, and we lay out clear conservation priorities that focus on protecting the small surviving populations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;/publication/campospotentialdistributionmodel-2013/&#34;&gt;Campos and Jack (2013) &lt;em&gt;Int J Primatol&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;/img/plots/conservation-priorities.png&#34; alt=&#34;seasonality&#34;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Urine Washing and Sniffing in Wild White-Faced Capuchins (Cebus capucinus): Testing Functional Hypotheses</title>
      <link>/publication/camposurinewashingsniffing-2007/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Feb 2007 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/camposurinewashingsniffing-2007/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
