<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Climate Variability on Fernando Alonso Campos</title>
    <link>https://tender-lumiere-15efb6.netlify.com/tags/climate-variability/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Climate Variability on Fernando Alonso Campos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Fernando Campos</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 22:33:41 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://tender-lumiere-15efb6.netlify.com/tags/climate-variability/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Climate variability and vital rates</title>
      <link>https://tender-lumiere-15efb6.netlify.com/project/climate-variability/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Sep 2017 22:33:41 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tender-lumiere-15efb6.netlify.com/project/climate-variability/</guid>
      <description>There is a growing need to understand how threatened species are affected by climate variability and climate change. This knowledge can uncover the limits of resiliency to climatic fluctuations and set the stage for informed conservation efforts. My colleagues and I have published important findings about how demography in natural primate populations varies in response to climate variability.
My first project with the PLHD working group examined the effects of temperature, rainfall, and large-scale climate oscillations on vital rates, including annual birth rates and survival rates.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Responses to Environmental Stress</title>
      <link>https://tender-lumiere-15efb6.netlify.com/project/environmental-stress/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2017 21:10:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://tender-lumiere-15efb6.netlify.com/project/environmental-stress/</guid>
      <description>Climate Seasonality Climate seasonality poses unique challenges to long-lived organisms in tropical dry forests: they must tolerate both long dry periods and long wet periods, and they must cope with the variable timing of transitions between wet and dry seasons. My colleagues and I have published studies that document how these challenges are met in a population of arboreal monkeys. These studies provided new insights into the strategies and behavioral tactics used by organisms to contend with periodic biophysical adversity.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>