<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Life History Evolution on Fernando Alonso Campos</title>
    <link>http://people.duke.edu/~fac13/tags/life-history-evolution/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Life History Evolution on Fernando Alonso Campos</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Fernando Campos</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 22:32:54 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/tags/life-history-evolution/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Sex differences in health and survival</title>
      <link>http://people.duke.edu/~fac13/project/sex-differences-health-survival/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 22:32:54 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://people.duke.edu/~fac13/project/sex-differences-health-survival/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;My postdoctoral work in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://sites.duke.edu/albertslab/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alberts lab&lt;/a&gt; at Duke is primarily focused on a phenomenon of modern human societies called the male-female health survival paradox, in which women live longer but experience higher rates of disability and poor health than men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a great deal of evidence that components of this phenomenon have a long evolutionary history in humans (reviewed by &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK242444/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Alberts et al. 2014&lt;/a&gt;), but interestingly, the paradox does not exist in baboons. Male baboons experience both higher mortality rates and steeper rates of age-related declines in health than do female baboons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These findings call for additional comparative studies to resolve evolutionary roots of the male-female health-survival paradox in humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My postdoctoral work examines how social relationships and age-related changes in hormones mediate sex differences in health and survival, using long-term life-history data and noninvasive health measures. The project&amp;rsquo;s broader goal is to improve our understanding of aging in the wild to gain new insights about aging in humans.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Responses to early-life adversity</title>
      <link>http://people.duke.edu/~fac13/project/early-life-adversity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Sep 2017 22:32:38 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://people.duke.edu/~fac13/project/early-life-adversity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Adversity during early life can reach far into the future to exert profound effects on health and well-being during adulthood.
Striking parallels exist between early-life effects in humans and in natural animal populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The leading conceptual models for early-life effects propose different evolutionary explanations for these phenomena.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Developmental constraints models&lt;/strong&gt; propose that harsh early-life conditions lead to developmental tradeoffs that prioritize immediate survival at the cost of reduced health, reproduction, and/or survival later in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Predictive adaptive response (PAR) models&lt;/strong&gt; posit that early-life conditions provide cues for predicting future conditions, leading to adaptive responses during development that maximize evolutionary fitness under predicted conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several important gaps in our understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;First&lt;/strong&gt;, which of these frameworks best explains the emergence of early-life effects in nonhuman primates?
&lt;strong&gt;Second&lt;/strong&gt;, to what extent are such effects embedded in our evolutionary history?
&lt;strong&gt;Third&lt;/strong&gt;, what are the optimal approaches to mitigating disparities in health and well-being that result from exposure early-life adversity in humans?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Motivated by these questions, I am leveraging a &lt;a href=&#34;../../project/plhd/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;database of life history data&lt;/a&gt; on seven natural primate populations to shed light on the mechanisms that underlie the far-reaching effects of early-life adversity and to test the universality of these effects among close relatives of humans.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Primate Life History Database</title>
      <link>http://people.duke.edu/~fac13/project/plhd/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Sep 2017 22:19:37 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://people.duke.edu/~fac13/project/plhd/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;h4 id=&#34;background-on-the-working-group&#34;&gt;Background on the Working Group&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://plhdb.org/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Primate Life History Database&lt;/a&gt; is a unique compilation of full life-course information from seven wild populations that have been studied for at least 30 years. The database contains standardized records for thousands of individual primates that have been followed from birth to death. These primate populations are some of the best-studied wild primates on earth. Formed over the course of several meetings from 2005 to 2007, the original core members of the PLHD include co-organizers Susan Alberts and Karen Strier, along with Jeanne Altmann, Diane Brockman, Anne Bronikowski, Marina Cords, Linda Fedigan, Bill Morris, Anne Pusey, Tara Stoinski. Following Diane&amp;rsquo;s retirement, Rich Lawler joined the working group in 2017.
&lt;p align = &#34;center&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;../../img/cards/plhd.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;PLHD Working Group&#34; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;The PLHD Working group in 2009.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My involvement with the PLHD working group began in 2015, when I was brought in to investigate the question of how &amp;ldquo;vital rates&amp;rdquo;&amp;mdash;that is, birth rates and death rates&amp;mdash;are affected by climate variability. This culminated in our 2017 paper:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;../../publication/campos_2017_does-climate-influence/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Campos et al. (2017) &lt;em&gt;Global Change Biology&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a post-doc in Susan Alberts&amp;rsquo; lab at Duke, I am continuing to work on several unresolved questions about life history evolution using this exceptionally valuable resource.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Maternal age effects on offspring</title>
      <link>http://people.duke.edu/~fac13/project/maternal-age-effects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Aug 2013 22:32:17 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://people.duke.edu/~fac13/project/maternal-age-effects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In collaboration with members of the &lt;a href=&#34;../../project/plhd/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Primate Life Histories working group&lt;/a&gt;, I am using long-term life-history data from seven primate species to investigate maternal age effects on reproductive performance and on offspring fitness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, we aim to determine:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;How variable are patterns of female reproductive aging (specifically interbirth interval changes during aging) across species? Can we reliably detect a signature of aging, or does this vary across species?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Are aspects of offspring fitness (survival and age at first reproduction) affected by maternal age?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;a. Does maternal age affect offspring’s age at first reproduction, and if so does it get better when mothers are middle-aged and worse when mothers are young or old?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;b. Does maternal age affect offspring survival to one year of age (or some such milestone), and if so does it get better when mothers are middle-aged and worse when mothers are young or old? Or some other pattern?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
